# Heather L. Borgard

Phone: 808-376-5084; Email: hbrgrd@gmail.com https://hborgard.github.io/

# **Summary**

Current Research Associate working at OHSU as an Informatician. Biomedical Engineering MSc graduate with 6 years of full-time research work experience at various universities in the US and Canada. I have a strong background in computer science and a passion for interdisciplinary collaboration.

#### **Technical Skills**

3D rendering and model creation (Amira, Avizo, Blender), Bioinformatics (R), Biomechanical simulation, CAD (Solid Works), Image segmentation, Mathematical modeling (MATLAB, Python, R), Medical Image Analysis (CT, MRI, DTI), Microcontroller programming, Programing languages (C, C#, C++, Java, Python), Statistical analysis (SPSS, R), VR/AR (Unity)

### **Education**

#### Master of Applied Science in Biomedical Engineering

University of British Columbia, Canada

May 2020

#### **Bachelor of Science in Biomedical Engineering**

Arizona State University, Tempe, AZ

### May 2015

## **Professional Experience**

#### Research Associate (Informatician I)

Oregon Health & Science University | Portland, OR

Jan. 2022-Present

- Developed mathematical model in Python and R using EHR data to predict patient appointment attendance and cancellations for OHSU hospital system
- Researched how baseline recordings affect data quality using national and local registries of ophthalmological data

#### **Bioinformatics Program Manager**

Jun. 2020-Jan. 2022

Research Corporation of University of Hawaii | Honolulu, HI

Oversees all administrative needs of a large research program (over 20 students and researchers) that focuses on cancer detection. Manages the budget planning, spending, and reporting of over 9 various grants for the entire Bioinformatics Core

Key Accomplishments:

- Co-authored three academic publications
- Helped the Core with grant submission to receive multiple NIH funded and infrastructure grants

### **Graduate Research Assistant**

Sep. 2017- Dec. 2019

University of British Columbia | Vancouver, Canada

• Collaborated with researchers and physicians to predict postoperative functional outcomes following mandibular reconstruction surgery through patient-specific computer simulations of mastication

### **Auxiliary Animal Care Technician**

Jul. 2018- Dec. 2019

University of British Columbia / Vancouver, Canada

Delivered superior animal care in a research facility contributing to research teams across the UBC campus

Research Assistant Nov. 2015- Jul. 2017

Midwestern University / Glendale, AZ

Managed the lab by creating policies and procedures, maintaining resources, and training students. Oversaw multiple research projects and interdisciplinary collaborations

**Key Accomplishments** 

• Contributed to the overall data collection, analysis, and writing of two publications

Capstone Project Aug. 2014 - May 2015

Arizona State University | Tempe, AZ

Universal Bioreactor for Tissue Engineering of Hollow Organs

• Interacted with physicians to construct a bioreactor for tissue engineering of hollow organs, involving extensive research of medical equipment systems, engineering design, and product development

# **Volunteering and Activities**

Overt Foundation Mar. 2021 – Sep. 2021

Grant Writer

• Perform extensive research and craft detailed proposals to obtain funding for patients of the program, outreach opportunities, and various administrative costs for the non-profit organization

#### **Teacher Partnership Volunteer**

Oct. 2017 - Dec. 2019

Let's Talk Science, University of British Columbia

• Designed science curriculums and led science activities and presentations for grades 4 through 8.

ProC.U.R.E Volunteer Feb. 2013 – Mar. 2015

Project C.U.R.E.

• Repaired, cleaned, packaged medical equipment for delivery to underserved areas.

EMT Volunteer Aug. 2013 – Dec. 2014

Arizona State University Student Emergency Medical Services (SEMS)

• Provided direct patient care on the ASU campus as a first responder.

#### Languages

English (Native)

Mandarin (Intermediate)